בוקר טוב Boker tov we are going to start we are starting
today's דף Daf is פ"ו Pei Vav eighty-six we start with the
bottom of פ"ה עמוד ב' Pei Hei Amud Bet
and where do we pick up we pick up with אמר ליה
רב פפא לאביי Amaleh Rav Papa l'Abaye thank
you so yes so we were talking about שחיטה שאינה ראויה Shechita
she'eina re'uya but two cases in which the sides would agree and
the case that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would agree that שחיטה שאינה
ראויה Shechita she'eina re'uya that שחיטה שאינה ראויה Shechita she'eina re'uya does
count is enough to make the animal not a טריפה Trefa even
if it also happened to be that because we considered it a
valid שחיטה Shechita you got off the hook about חולין בעזרה. Chullin
Ba'azarah. So now that we're introducing חולין בעזרה Chullin Ba'azarah we're going
to spend the next little bit wrapping up the חולין בעזרה Chullin
Ba'azarah discussion. So we start with אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי Amaleh
Rav Papa l'Abaye וסבר. V'savar. So now with the line starting with
the word וסבר V'savar that is twenty lines from the bottom. וסבר
רבי שמעון חולין בעזרה דאורייתא היא? V'savar Rabbi Shimon Chullin Ba'azarah De'oraita
hee? Does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon really hold חולין בעזרה Chullin Ba'azarah
is a biblical concern? Now how did we know that he did?
Well one of the reasons is because we were trying to say
that since שחיטה שאינה ראויה Shechita she'eina re'uya gets you off the
hook
because you remember if they say that you שחטed shecht a טריפה
Trefa חולין בעזרה Chullin Ba'azarah that maybe since it was getting you
off the hook for חולין בעזרה Chullin Ba'azarah it should also be
a non-שחיטה Shechita the animal should be a נבילה. Neveila. So obviously
that means that we're dealing with biblical level concepts. If it was
only a דרבנן Derabbanan concept then it wouldn't have fundamentally gotten you
off the hook. That's one point. The other point רש"י Rashi says
which is going to be borne out in a minute in the
גמרא Gemara is that if it were hold on one
second let me just double check
this one
minute right because רש"י Rashi says like this רש"י Rashi says why
would חולין בעזרה Chullin Ba'azarah now by the way when there's a
discussion whether חולין בעזרה Chullin Ba'azarah is biblical or rabbinic it seems
to be although there's two ways you could ask the question one
way you could ask the question is does that mean whether it's
biblically restricted to שחט shecht a non-קרבן Korban in the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash whether there's a biblical prohibition? The other question is that
as we've seen what happens when you שחט shecht a non-קרבן Korban
in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash the meat is forbidden to be
eaten so maybe the question is is that prohibition to eat the
meat of an animal שחטed shecht in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
a non-קרבן Korban is that a biblical prohibition? Meaning there's one that
focuses on the act and there's the other that would focus on
the meat. Now the reason that the גמרא Gemara asks this is
because if you look in the תורה Torah you're never going to
see the תורה Torah say anywhere you shall not slaughter a non-קרבן
Korban in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. It says you know it
speaks about slaughtering your non-קרבנות Korbanot outside it says and it speaks
about slaughtering קרבנות Korbanot inside okay but it never actually says that
when you can't go to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash you shall
slaughter your animals outside so from there we can infer oh you
can only slaughter them outside you can't slaughter them inside but it's
never explicit. So the question can be raised is this prohibition really
biblical and whether the meat is really forbidden to be eaten biblically?
Now רש"י Rashi says the reason why it sounds like it is
biblical according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is because רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon applied his
technicality about שחיטה שאינה ראויה Shechita she'eina re'uya to get you off
the hook by שחטing shecht חולין בעזרה. Chullin Ba'azarah. But here we
get to actually an interesting point and it's too bad Rifka isn't
here because I know she's often sort of you know sort of
raising the issue about the technicalities of the גמרא Gemara as opposed
to the reason. The גמרא Gemara actually here assumes that if something
is a biblical law then we can expect that there might be
technicalities there's formal definitions what constitutes a שחיטה Shechita if this doesn't
constitute שחיטה Shechita you're off the hook. Okay that makes sense if
it's a biblical law and there are formal definitions but if it's
a דרבנן Derabbanan law the גמרא Gemara is assuming we should more
generally look towards the concerns that are at play and not bother
so much with the technicalities. So therefore רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
if you שחט shecht חולין בעזרה Chullin Ba'azarah and it's a טריפה
Trefa you're off the hook because it's שחיטה שאינה ראויה. Shechita she'eina
re'uya. The גמרא Gemara says well that makes sense if it's biblical
then on the technical point we don't call that a שחיטה Shechita
but if it's a דרבנן Derabbanan issue why would we not want
you to שחט shecht an animal in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
a non-קרבן? Korban? Why would we not want you to do that?
What do you think if it was a דרבנן Derabbanan concern?
Because you might you'll take it out
right you'll confuse it with
קרבנות Korbanot that you're going to treat this as חולין Chullin the
way you're going to act with it won't be the way you'll
act with קרבנות Korbanot but people will think it's a קרבן Korban
and it'll lead to just a lot of challenging of boundaries and
confusion. If that's the concern who cares about the technicality whether it's
a שחיטה ראויה Shechita re'uya or not a שחיטה ראויה? Shechita re'uya?
We don't want you doing this act in the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash and get everybody confused. So therefore the גמרא Gemara says since
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying you're off the hook when you
שחט shecht חולין בעזרה Chullin Ba'azarah if it's not a fit שחיטה
Shechita if it's a שחיטה שאינה ראויה Shechita she'eina re'uya that proves
that we're dealing with a technical concern a formal concern and therefore
that makes sense if it's biblical but if it's דרבנן... Derabbanan... Those
formal issues should not bother us. So we're going to see the
גמרא Gemara is going to discuss whether it's biblical or not. But
what I think is very nice is about implicitly in this גמרא
Gemara and again it's funny because רבקה's Rivka always saying, well who
cares about these you know technicalities what about the larger issue? The
גמרא Gemara actually is implicitly saying no when we're dealing with תורה
Torah law and the תורה Torah says certain things you שחט, shecht,
you do X, you do Y, you do you know A, B,
and C, we have to formally define those things. But if it's
rabbinic law then we can more look towards our goals, our purposes
being met or not being met. You had a query.
Yeah. When you say it's a קרבן korban do you have to
specifically
say הרי עלי קרבן? harei alai korban?
Or you could say הרי זו, harei zu, yes.
So you wouldn't be confused.
Well, you maybe not be confused but even even you may be
you know even if you didn't sanctify it but you know when
you start acting in certain ways even if your mind you know
better your acts can very often affect the way you perceive things
even if at some at some abstract level you realize you didn't
make it a קרבן. korban. But besides how you're feeling about it
it's also a question of the impression you're creating on other people.
Other people don't know what you've sanctified or not.
Everyone's going into the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. Oh you don't have to do it in the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash and not everybody sees you know not everybody is
there for every act and not everybody knows exactly what the story
is.
But wouldn't the בעל הבית baal habayis be in charge of whatever?
Yeah but again no you bring an animal you could have sanctified
it a week ago a minute ago and other people who are
looking are much more impacted by what they see than by knowing
those exact details.
Okay, go ahead David.
Could you just
clarify for a second is the reason שחיטה shechita in the עזרה
azarah is not permitted is because it's not specifically permitted
and then it's like just?
Yes, that's right. Or is it rabbinic legislation in which case we
care about the טעמא דקרא ta'ama dikra itself?
Well, okay, so that's exactly the question. If it's rabbinic legislation then
we're assuming it's because of concerns about that confusion and so on
and therefore we shouldn't care about these technicalities. If it's not rabbinic
legislation then to some degree and this also explains why we are
less factor in reasons when we're dealing with biblical law and תורה
Torah law. It's because like in a way there's a certain humility
there. We're not high you know who tells us exactly what the
reasons are that we can regularly shape things based on those
reasons? לא דרשינן טעמא דקרא. Lo darshinan ta'ama dikra. I mean how
do we even know exactly what the reason is? So we have
to go more by just a formalistic approach about does it qualify
as a שחיטה, shechita, you know, are those criteria being met? So
if it's—so that's the question—if it's שחיטה shechita if it's biblical then
we—you know we don't know what the reason is but we do
know the תורה Torah says שחט shecht outside the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash don't שחט shecht a non-קרבן korban in the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash.
If it's biblical it's אסור assur because it's not מותר. muttar. So
without specific permission it's אסור. assur.
Yes, but the גמרא Gemara goes further. The גמרא Gemara sort of
says you know the גמרא Gemara says the פסוק pasuk says וזבחת
כי ירחק ממך המקום Vezavachta ki yirchak mimcha hamakom when you're far
from the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash וזבחת vezavachta you shall slaughter and then it
infers right so you could just say you don't have the permission
to slaughter when you're not far away. But the גמרא Gemara reads
the verse if it is biblical and it's not an אסמכתא asmachta
you're not allowed to meaning you know right meaning meaning it's like
a it's like a negative that's inferred from a positive. You can
slaughter far away, you're not allowed to slaughter when you are close.
I'm not sure what you're saying there meaning what I'm hearing you
say is that well maybe then the meat is just like a
נבילה neveila because the תורה Torah didn't allow you it doesn't count
as a שחיטה. shechita. Is that what you're saying? Am I understanding?
I was going to say I'm trying to figure out why we
can't play handball in the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. Oh play handball in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash because
it's not specifically permitted.
Oh right
so that's not what we're saying. We're not saying that you can't
the only things you can do are things that are specifically permitted.
We're saying that the תורה Torah specifically tells you שחט shecht outside
and the implicit message is don't שחט shecht inside. Okay, if that
is the real read of the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so let's take
a look. So now the גמרא Gemara continues, okay, so does רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon really hold that this is biblical that he could
apply his technical consideration? וסבר רבי שמעון שחיטת חולין בעזרה דאורייתא היא?
V'savar Rebbi Shimon shechitat chullin ba'azarah d'oraita hi? אמר ליה אין, Amar
lei in, yes, והתנן vehatnan we have a משנה. Mishna. The משנה
Mishna says רבי שמעון אומר חולין שנשחטו בעזרה ישרפו
באש
Rebbi Shimon
omer chullin shenishchetu ba'azarah yisarfu ba'eish that if you שחט shecht חולין
chullin in the עזרה azarah you burn them in a fire.
וכן חיה שנשחטה בעזרה V'chen chaya shenishcheta ba'azarah
even if it's not a בהמה behema even if it's a חיה,
chaya, right, which gets us into the covering of the blood question.
You also burn it. אי אמרת בשלמא דאורייתא Ei amart bishlama d'oraita
if it's biblical היינו דגזרינן חיה אטו בהמה hainu degazrinan chaya atu
behema
then we would understand why you extended it to a חיה chaya
that even though a חיה chaya can never be a קרבן korban
but you know it's one step removed from a biblical concern which
is by a בהמה. behema. אלא אי אמרת דרבנן Ela ei amart
derabbanan if the whole thing is rabbinic בהמה מאי טעמא behema mai
ta'ama why can you not שחט shecht a cow in the עזרה
azarah if it's not a קרבן? korban? דילמא אתי למיכל קדשים בחוץ
Dilma ati lemeichal kodashim bachutz as Charlie said because then you'll take
your cow outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and you'll eat it
and people would then start bringing קדשים kodashim outside of the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash and you're you know confusing the boundary. Okay, but
that's a rabbinic concern. So if it's a rabbinic concern by a
cow היא גופא גזירה hi gufa gezeira it itself is a safeguard
ואנן ניקום ונגזור גזירה לגזירה ve'anan neikum venigzor gezeira ligzeira do you
think we're going to make a safeguard against a safeguard? If even
a cow you can't do because of what it might lead to,
then a deer is a, you know, is a double safeguard. Don't
do a non-קרבן Korban deer because you might come to do a
non-קרבן Korban cow. And don't do a non-קרבן Korban cow because you're
going to get people confused. So we wouldn't make a double safeguard.
But if it's biblical, then we can understand why it applies to
a חיה chaya as well. Now רש״י Rashi actually says that if
it's biblical, it's not even a גזירה gezeira by חיה. chaya. This
gets also to the point about if it's biblical, we don't, you
know, we just are formalistic. If it says don't שחט shecht outside,
to only שחט shecht outside, don't שחט shecht inside, it would apply
equally to a חיה chaya as to a בהמה. behemah. And even
if for some reason it would only apply biblically to a בהמה,
behemah, we could understand a one degree extension to a חיה. chaya.
But if the whole thing is rabbinic, to apply it to a
חיה chaya would be a double protection, and that's for a double
גזירה, gezeira, and that far we would not go. Okay, רבי חייא,
Rebbi Chiya, that's the end of that. Now we get back to
our, you know, our more central issues here of כיסוי הדם. kisuy
hadam. But again, the fascinating thing about that is the assumption that
if it's biblical, these formal concerns of שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita she'eina
re'uyah are relevant. If it's rabbinic, we're not so concerned about maybe
formal issues and technicalities as much as are our concerns being addressed
or not. Now רבי ינאי, Rebbi Yannai, רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya נפלה
ליה יניבא בקינתני. nafla leh yaniva bekintnei. רבי ינאי, Rebbi Yannai, רבי
חייא Rebbi Chiya had a certain type of a worm or an
infestation in his flax. And apparently the way to get rid of
this infestation was to use chicken blood. And that somehow drove these,
you know, bugs out. So אתא לקמיה דרבי. ata l'kamei d'Rebbe. He
came to רבי. Rebbe. Now there's a problem because if you want
to get chicken blood, if you שחט shecht a chicken, you need
to cover the blood. So how do you get chicken blood? So
אמר ליה, amar leh, so he says, שקול עוף ושחוט על בוביתא
דמיא. shekol of ushchot al bubita d'maya. Take a bird and שחט
shecht it over a puddle of water.
Or actually not a puddle of water, רש״י Rashi says it means
the water that you are soaking the flax in. So you've got
your flax, it's soaking in water, שחט shecht the blood on it.
The blood will go into the water and then it'll and that'll
drive away this infestation. דמורח דמא ושביק ליה demureach dama veshavik leh
and they'll smell the blood and they'll abandon the flax. So היכי
עביד הכי? heichi avid hachi? How could you do that? והתניא, vehatanya,
השוחט וצריך לדם, hashochet v'tzarich l'dam, if you שחט shecht and you're
not even interested in the meat, you just want the blood, חייב
לכסות. chayav l'chatzot. You still have to cover the blood. So although
we said that the meat might have to be fit to be
eaten, it has to be שחיטה ראויה, shechita re'uyah, you don't have
to be actually wanting to eat the meat. Even if you've no
intent to eat the meat, you only want the blood, you have
to cover the blood. So it's not about wanting to eat the
meat or planning, it's about it being able to be fit to
be eaten. One minute. So therefore if here, even if you don't
not interested in the meat, the blood needs to be covered. So
how are you going to go ahead and use that, you know,
and spill it in the water and use it? So כיצד יעשה?
ketzad ya'aseh? What do you do if you want the blood? או
נוחרו או עוקרו, o nochro o okro, don't שחט shecht it. Either
like either you know, you know,
slaughter it, rip out the סימנים, simanim, or kill it in another
way. Kill the animal, get out the blood without שחיטה. shechita. And
that's the only way you can get blood out of an animal,
out of a bird or a חיה chaya without having to cover
it. Okay.
So, so כי אתא רב דימי, ki ata Rav Dimi, when רב
דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמר צא טרוף
אמר ליה. amar tzei t'rof amar leh. He did, you're right. He
did not tell him just שחט shecht it in water. He said
make the bird a טריפה. treifa. And then שחט shecht it. Okay.
כי אתא רבין ki ata Ravin אמר צא נחור אמר ליה. amar
tzei nechor amar leh. He said, don't, he said,
he didn't say שחט shecht it, he said, you know, go kill
it. Kill it in a way to get the blood, which isn't
שחטינג. shechting. So, you're right, he didn't say סתם stam שחט. shecht.
He said do it in a way that it's either a טריפה
treifa or not a שחיטה. shechita. So למאן דאמר צא טרוף, l'man
d'amar tzei t'rof, the one who said that he told him make
it a טריפה, treifa, מאי טעמא לא אמר צא נחור? mai ta'ama
lo amar tzei nechor? Why did he say that he did not
say go and just, you know, kill it as opposed to
שחט shecht it? וכי תימא v'chei teima קסבר אין שחיטה לעוף מן
התורה kasavar ein shechita l'of min hatorah ונחירה היא היא שחיטתו, v'nechira
hi hi shechitatu, maybe because he held that remember going way back
to an early to the very beginning of the מסכת. masechet. There's
an opinion that biblically you don't need to שחט shecht birds. So
if biblically you don't need to שחט shecht birds, you'd have to
cover the blood of a bird even if you didn't שחט shecht
it. So there's no way out of covering the blood of a
bird, right? Because even a non-שחיטה shechita is has no different significance
than a
שחיטה. shechita. Because either way the meat is fit to be eaten
if you don't really need a שחיטה. shechita. So what's the only,
so what's the only way you're going to prevent the meat from
being fit to be eaten? By making the bird first a טריפה
treifa and then killing it. Now this is also ironic, because you
would have thought that how does טריפה treifa function? טריפה treifa functions
by making the שחיטה shechita not effective. But here we're saying you
might not need a שחיטה shechita by bird. If the bird just
died, you know, you shot it in the head, it would be
kosher. But טריפה treifa adds a level of prohibition independent of the
fact that the that there was no necessary שחיטה. shechita. Okay. So
therefore maybe he couldn't say kill it some other way, he had
to say make it a טריפה. treifa. And that would be the
only way to make the meat not fit to be eaten and
therefore you could use the blood. והתניא, vehatanya, but you can't say
that because we taught. רבי Rebbe אומר, omer, כאשר צויתיך, ka'asher tziviticha,
I have I commanded you. מלמד שנצטוה משה melamed shenitzva Moshe et
It says you shall slaughter as I have commanded you. This is
the only verse that indicates that there is a procedure to do
the שחיטה. shechita. It says you will slaughter your animals as I
have commanded. So, מלמד שנצטוה משה Melamed shenitztave Moshe על הושט ועל
הקנה al haveshet veal hakane the two... the two סימנים, simanim, the
trachea and the esophagus, or the esophagus and the trachea, ועל רוב
אחד בעוף, veal rov echad beof, the majority of one of the
סימנים simanim in a bird, ועל רוב שנים בבהמה, veal rov shnayim
bebehema, the majority of two in a בהמה. behema. I have to
remind you of the great little acronym that Tosafot pointed out. It
wasn't in the גמרא, Gemara, but he says it's a play on
the word כאשר, Kaasher, which is...
which is... the אשר Asher is... how did we read it? Oh,
if you read כאשר Kaasher backwards, it's רובו של אחד כמוהו, rubo
shel echad kamoho, the majority of one סימן siman counts like the
סימן siman itself. Or... he did something else with that, I forget
also to get the אחד בעוף echad beof and the שנים בבהמה.
shnayim bebehema. The אלף alef might be אחד echad and the שין
shin שנים, shnayim, but I forget the other דרשה. drasha. Anyway, so
Rabbi Chiya was Rebbi's... Rabbi Chiya went, remember he had the problem,
and he went to Rebbi, and Rebbi himself is the one who
says that you have to do שחיטה shechita for a bird and
that's biblical. Biblical requirement to do שחיטה shechita for a bird. So
if that's true, what's the version that Rebbi says make it a
טריפה? treifa? Why would he say that Rebbi just said, you know,
kill it some way without שחיטה, shechita, and then you have to
get out of covering the blood? So גמרא Gemara says, top of
פ"ו עמוד א', pe-vov amud alef, לא מיבעיא קאמר. lo mibaya kaamar.
It goes without saying. לא מיבעיא צא ונחור דלאו שחיטה היא כלל.
lo mibaya tze venachor delav shechita hi klal. Of course, one way
to not have to cover the blood is just kill it without
שחיטה. shechita. That goes without saying. אבל צא וטרוף, aval tze utrof,
but if you just made it a טריפה, treifa, אימא שחיטה שאינה
ראויה שמה שחיטה, eima shechita she'eina re'uya shema shechita, I might think
that we generally ruled that a שחיטה shechita that is not fit
counts as a שחיטה, shechita, right? So even if the animal is
a טריפה treifa maybe you still have to cover the blood,
ואיבעי כיסוי veiba'ei kisuy and you'll have to cover the blood, קמשמע
לן kamashma lan that you don't. כדרבי חייא בר אבא, kideRabbi Chiya
bar Abba, like Rabbi Chiya bar Abba in the beginning, if you
remember yesterday, Rabbi Chiya bar Abba said Rebbi, and that's who we're
talking about here, Rebbi who edited the משנה, Mishnah, said that even
though in general he ruled שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita she'eina re'uya counts,
but by covering the blood it doesn't, since by covering the blood
the תורה Torah says ואכלת veachalta that you will eat, meat you
will eat, it has to be שחיטה ראויה. shechita re'uya. So one
version is his Rabbi... Rabbi Chiya wanted the blood, what did Rebbi
tell him to do? Make the bird a טריפה treifa and then
שחט shecht it. And therefore since it's a שחיטה shechita that's not
fit to eat the meat, you don't have to cover the blood
because at least here if it's not fit to eat the meat,
as... normally that would still be a שחיטה, shechita, but here it's
not. And here you don't have to cover the blood.
Now, ולמאן דאמר צא ונחור, ul’man de'amar tze venachor, the one who
said go and... just kill it without שחיטה, shechita, מאי טעמא לא
אמר צא וטרוף? mai tama lo amar tze utrof? Why
not say, why doesn't he have the version that Rebbi said make
it a טריפה? treifa? וכי תימא קסבר שחיטה שאינה ראויה שמה שחיטה,
vekhi teima kasavar shechita she'eina re'uya shema shechita,
maybe because he thinks that Rebbi holds that even if it was
a טריפה, treifa, it still counts here, that a not fit שחיטה
shechita counts even by covering the blood? והאמר רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן, ve'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, but
didn't we say at the beginning of yesterday, ראה רבי דברי רבי
שמעון בכיסוי הדם ושנה בלשון חכמים? ra'a Rebbi divrei Rabbi Shimon bekhisuy
hadam veshana belashon chakhamim? That when it comes to covering the blood,
Rebbi rules like Rabbi שמעון, Shimon, Rebbi says that when it comes
to covering the blood, the שחיטה shechita has to be fit. Since
the verse said that you will eat, the שחיטה shechita has to
be fit, and here Rebbi rules like that. So since by covering
the blood Rebbi demands that the שחיטה shechita be fit, why didn't
he say just make it a טריפה treifa according to this version?
Why did he say kill it without שחיטה? shechita? So גמרא Gemara
also says לא מיבעיא קאמר. lo mibaya kaamar. It goes without saying.
לא מיבעיא צא וטרוף דשחיטה שאינה ראויה לא שמה שחיטה, lo mibaya
tze utrof deshechita she'eina re'uya lo shema shechita, certainly if you make
it a טריפה treifa you won't have to cover the blood because
here by covering the blood if it's not a fit שחיטה shechita
it doesn't count. אבל צא ונחור, aval tze venachor, but when you're
just killing it without שחיטה, shechita, אימא אימא דאפילו שחיטה לאו מן
התורה eima eima de'afilu shechita lav min haTorah
going back to what we suggested before, maybe biblically you don't have
to do שחיטה shechita at all? וניחשיב עשייה זו שחיטתה, venikhshav asiya
zu shechitata, so even if you don't שחט shecht it, even if
you kill it some other way, it counts and you would have
to cover the blood, ואיבעי כיסוי veiba'ei kisuy and you'd have to
cover the blood, קמשמע לן כאשר צויתיך. kamashma lan kaasher tziviticha.
So therefore it's saying no, here you do have to do שחיטה,
shechita, you do have to do שחיטה shechita biblically, and therefore one
way to get out of it is to kill it without שחיטה.
shechita. So what's the אופשט upshat of this and then I'll take
the question? Actually I'll finish to the משנה Mishnah and then I'll
take questions. The אופשט upshat is number one is again reminding us
that even if normally שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita she'eina re'uya counts, it
doesn't count here because here it says אשר יאכל, asher ye'akhel, the
meat has to be fit. Number two, even though the meat has
to be fit to eat and it doesn't... you don't... it doesn't
matter whether you want to eat it or don't want to eat
it, so if you just want the blood, tough luck, since the
meat is fit to be eaten you have to cover the blood,
and then you're stuck because you just wanted the blood. So what
are you going to do? So you basically get the blood without
doing either שחיטה shechita at all, you just don't שחט shecht it,
you shoot it in the head or you שחט shecht it from
behind or some way you're not even doing שחיטה shechita at all,
or you make it a טריפה treifa and then you שחט shecht
it. And either way it's not a שחיטה shechita or not a
fit שחיטה, shechita, either way you can then use the blood, you
don't have to cover it. Let's read to the משנה Mishnah and
then I'll answer the questions. ומי נפל ליה יניבא בכיטני, umi nafla
Yaniva bekitnei, how could...
how could Rabbi Chiya have had an infestation in his flax? Why
not? והאמר רב... ve'amar Rav... ואמר רבין בר אבא ואמרי לה רב
אבין בר שבא Veamar Ravin bar Abba v'amrey lei Rav Avin bar
Shaba משעלו בני הגולה mishalu b'nei hagola from the time that the
people from the diaspora came up to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael פסקו
הזיקין והזועות והרוחות והרעמים. pasku hazikin ve'hazva'os ve'haruchos ve'hara'amim.
You know they were righteous people that came up. Now which
עליה aliyah
was he talking about? He was not talking about the עליה ראשונה
Aliyah Rishona when it came when the time of the first בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash of the second בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash רש"י Rashi
says that we're talking here like in the later period basically at
the time really you know when there was some migration towards רש"י
Rashi says you know in at the later I mean we're always
hearing about you know people that are going to ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael to learn and so on. We actually hear at the sort
of at the beginning of the תנאים Tanaic period you know if
you remember the famous story that ערב פסח Erev Pesach fell out
on שבת Shabbos and they didn't know if you could bring a
פסח Pesach on שבת. Shabbos. And then they said oh is there
anybody here who knows the tradition about it? It says oh הלל
הבבלי, Hillel HaBavli, Hillel the Babylonian came you know he knows what
the tradition is. We forget that Hillel originally came back from בבל
Bavel even though he founded the whole you know whatever that you
know that whole school and so on. So anyway so in that
later in that period of the תנאים Tannaim when people started when
we had these righteous people coming up from בבל Bavel so then
all of these wonderful things happened. פסקו הזיקין והזועות Pasku hazikin ve'hazva'os
the like you know the the earth tremors and the the harsh
winds maybe like the tornadoes והרוחות והרעמים ve'haruchos ve'hara'amim again these harsh
winds and רעמים ra'amim is I guess thunder I assume they had
some form of thunder but okay anyway you know all these terrible
types of
weather events ולא החמיץ יינם velo hechmit yeinam the wine did not
become fermented spoiled it didn't turn into vinegar soured not fermented soured
ולא לקה פשתנם velo laka pishtanam and here's the key point the
flax was which free from infestation. Okay so when these righteous people
came up so who are they talking about? So once this statement
was made ונתנו חכמים עיניהם ברבי חייא ובניו venasnu chachamim eineihem bi'Rebbe
Chiya u'vanav so everybody looked towards Rebbe Chiya and his kids they
figured those were the people that were being referred to they were
the righteous most righteous people. So therefore the same Rebbe Chiya who
according to this story was the one who accounted for all these
positive things and free from infestation how could he himself have had
the infestation? So what does the גמרא Gemara say? So the גמרא
Gemara says כי מהני זכותייהו אעלמא ki mahani zchusaihu a'alma
his merit helps for the rest of the world אדידיה לא adehadihu
lo but it didn't help for himself. It's like you know the
what is it the shoemaker's children are always the ones last ones
to get the shoes. לא lo if you come in the middle
you'll have to wait. לא lo לא lo כדרב יהודה אמר רב
ki'de'Rav Yehuda amar Rav like Rav Yehuda said Rav דאמר רב יהודה
אמר רב de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav בכל יום ויום בת קול
יוצאת ואומרת כל העולם כולו ניזון בשביל חנניה בני וחנניה בני די
לו בקב חרובים מערב שבת לערב שבת bechol yom vayom bas kol
yotzes ve'omeres kol ha'olam kulo nizon bishvil Chananya beni ve'Chananya beni dai
lo bekav charuvin me'erev Shabbos le'erev Shabbos that every day a heavenly
voice comes out and says the whole world is sustained because of
the merit of Chananya my son and Chananya my son
sustains himself on just a certain measure of these
חרובים charuvim bucksters right for you know from one week to the
next. Now presumably the point here being not a that it wasn't
just a choice right if it was just a choice then it
would not be a relevant point it means that he all he
has to all he has to sustain himself is this limited amount
of food even though the right if he was just choosing I
understand that normally we assume that might mean that he's choosing you
know right an ascetic lifestyle right but the relevance here seems to
be emphasizing not a sound of choice he he all he has
to support himself is this little thing but his merit is great
for everybody else so people can reflect on the theological significance of
that but I'll take two questions yes go ahead you had a
question.
If you kill the animal so then it's kind of a נבילה
neveila right?
If you kill the animal yes it's a נבילה neveila
right is that a concern?
No it's just a טומאה tuma concern it's no different than a
טריפה treifa and if we're not living in a world of טומאה
וטהרה tuma v'tahara it's no real concern okay.
All
right so anyway I didn't have really enough chance I'm you know
to reflect on the significance of this about I mean other than
sort of reflect about how this is true you know not in
a sort of a metaphysical way but it is true for you
know a lot of people in terms of their lives that people
that dedicate themselves to you know helping other people very often you
know a they suffer a lot for it and b they don't
take care of themselves they prioritize other people's needs over their own
needs you know so there is sometimes a certain reality about that
type of a צדיק טיפוס tzaddik tipus that really gives to everybody
else and puts himself on the bottom of the list and sometimes
also you know is like you know the ווארט vort that they
say it says you know העוסקים בצרכי ציבור באמונה הקדוש ברוך הוא
ישלם שכרם ha'oskim b'tzorchei tzibbur b'emuna Hakadosh Baruch Hu yeshalem scharam because
nobody else is being משלם שכרם meshalem scharam so anyway but here
it's even saying it at some metaphysical level but maybe you know
that's the point that keeps your righteousness pure is when you're doing
it for as when other people are getting it and not yourself
yes.
Next question. Suffering, that's an interesting perspective too. Right. All right.
Yes. So we're back in חולין Chullin and we're talking about animals
he's moving on and חרובים, Charuvim, but again this is a גמרא
Gemara that's borrowed from תענית, Taanis, you know this is not the
original state place where this תענית Taanis and ברכות, Brachos, it's just
being imported here to make the comparison. Okay, now we move on.
חרש שוטה וקטן ששחטו ואחרים רואים אותם, Cheresh shoteh vekatan sheshachatu veacherim
roim otam, that we might even catch up today. So remember this?
It's like a minute ago we quoted the question whether there's a
שחיטה shechitah in birds in the תורה, Torah, now we are going
back all the way back to the first משנה Mishna of the
מסכת. masechet. So, חרש שוטה וקטן Cheresh shoteh vekatan that שחטו shachtu
and other people watched them, what does the first משנה Mishna tell
us? It's a כשר שחיטה kasher shechitah if they observed and saw
that it was good. So if it's a כשר שחיטה, kasher shechitah,
חייב לכסות, chayav lechasot, you have to cover the blood. בינם לבין
עצמם, Beinam levein atzmam,
if nobody was watching them, so now we don't know if it
was a כשר שחיטה kasher shechitah or not, right? Because we're concerned
that if they שחטו shachtu without being observed maybe they didn't do
it correctly. So what would you say? You would say, okay, you
don't know, so what? Cover the blood without a ברכה, bracha, right?
That logically would be what we say. פטור מלכסות, Patur milechasot, don't
cover the blood. Now why do you think? Because what will happen
if you cover the blood of this animal that they שחטו, shachtu,
what are people going to assume? People are going to assume it
was a good שחיטה shechitah and they'll eat from the meat. So
rather than cover the blood without a ברכה, bracha, better not to
cover the blood so that people won't come to eat
from
the
meat. וכן לעניין אותו ואת בנו, Vechein le'inyan oto ve'et beno, and
also for the going back to the last פרק, perek, שחיטה shechting
an animal and its child, ששחטו sheshachtu they שחטו shachtu one ואחרים
רואים אותם, veacherim roim otam, if people observed it and know it
was a שחיטה, shechitah, then fine, אסור לשחוט אחריהם, assur lishchot achareihem,
don't שחט shacht the next the child on the same
day. בינם לבין עצמם, Beinam levein atzmam, if however they שחטו shachtu
and nobody was observing, so you don't know if it was good,
now we've got a little bit of a problem. Okay, רבי מאיר
מתיר לשחוט אחריהם. Rabbi Meir matir lishchot achareihem. First of all you
get רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, which seems like crazy. He's saying go
ahead, שחט shacht afterwards, which is what? Like I understand you want
to play it safe and you don't want people to get the
wrong message, but maybe it was a good שחיטה shechitah and if
you שחט shacht on the same day you're violating שחיטה shechting the
calf on the same day. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir we're going
to have to figure out. But let's see what the חכמים Chachamim
say. וחכמים אוסרים, Vechachamim osrim, they don't let you שחט shacht on
the same day. Now, okay, I get why they don't let me
שחט shacht on the same day because maybe it was good and
maybe I will transgress if I שחט shacht on this day. But
why am I not concerned that people will get the wrong message,
right? People will see that I'm not שוחט shochet today and then
they'll come to eat from the meat of the first שחיטה. shechitah.
Why am I not concerned about that?
Because you don't have to שחט. shacht.
Ah, so you would say there's a big difference between doing something
and not doing something. If I cover the blood, I'm sending out
a message that this was a good שחיטה. shechitah. If I'm not
שוחט shochet the calf today, okay, I decided today I would have
a I would have a salad. There's not people aren't observing the
act of not שחיטה. shechting. So therefore that's one point. And the
other point is, in the first case all you're doing is not
doing a positive מצוה. mitzvah. So we know that, that חז"ל Chazal
can tell us don't do a positive מצוה, mitzvah, be
passive, don't do don't do don't do a מצוה. mitzvah. But here
even if they were concerned, right, that people would get the wrong
message, but they can't tell me to violate a prohibition or to
even possibly violate a prohibition and שחט shacht today. So here they
have to tell me, if the issue's about violating, you got to
play it safe and don't שחט shacht today whatever the concerns are.
ומודים בשחט, Umodim beshachat, but everybody agrees that if you did שחט,
shacht, שאינו סופג את הארבעים, she'eino sofeg et ha'arba'im, you don't get
40 lashes because maybe the שחיטה shechitah of the חרש שוטה וקטן
cheresh shoteh vekatan was good, so it's all about a
doubt.
Yes.
Covering the blood כיסוי הדם kisuy hadam is for חיה chayah and
אותו ואת בנו oto ve'et beno is for בהמה. behemah. Yes. Different
scenarios. So you got a different an additional difference between them.
You are correct. So totally different cases. One case is with חיה,
chayah, do you cover the blood, the other case is with a
בהמה behemah and do you do אותו ואת בנו. oto ve'et beno.
Yes, very good point. You're right, they're different cases. Yes.
Suppose this case of אותו ואת בנו oto ve'et beno and the
last case where we were talking about
whether it was really שחיטה shechitah or not with an עוף. of.
Right. There's there's this issue of relationship that if we're not going
to consume, if we can't consume, then we can kill the animal
anyway we want.
Right. You find that troubling?
Not troubling, but undermining of the idea of צער בעלי חיים tza'ar
ba'alei chayim underlying the the issue.
Yeah, I mean because what you but the point though being is
that what your real question is is that should there be a
more blanket, meaning if we sort of see that we're given license
to שחט shacht these animals when we need them for our use
and so on, shouldn't it be a general problem to just wantonly
sort of שחט shacht destroy the animal? Meaning, if שחיטה shechitah is
regulating how we're taking their lives, shouldn't it start with a regulation
about...
I'm not going to tell the הקב"ה KBH how to how to
write code.
הקב"ה, KBH, הקדוש ברוך הוא, Hakadosh Baruch Hu, right, yeah,
but I am saying that it doesn't ring out that this is
about concern about animals, this is concern about animals that we're going
to eat.
Right. Right. You know, and that gets to, I think the types
of questions that Riska raises, which is, is that, you know,
we're
dealing here with in sort of, you know, right, sort of defined
context and formal criteria and you know we're not sort of always
trying to say how are we addressing... meaning, I don't know that
within the context of why are there particular laws of not שוחט-ing
shecht this and the child on the same day that we can't
say that that is the value of concern for animals applied in
this
context. What I do know is, is that it's not like this
value of concern for animals just, you know, all of a sudden,
you know, logically extends to its fullest to its fullest extent.
It is not שוחט-ing, shecht it's not don't kill,
it's don't שחט, shecht, it's don't שחט. shecht. Right.
Right. No, I understand that, but I I still think that there's
a difference between saying we don't take the value... look, let's say
it wasn't about concern of animals, let's say it was about our
own callousness. Why aren't we concerned about our own callousness if we
if we kill them in a way other than שחיטה shechita we're
even being more callous. Right? So any type of thing is why
are we limiting it to שוחט-ing shecht versus other ways of killing?
That's why I started by saying it's about relationship. And and what's
our relationship with this animal that we're going to eat.
So you think that the callous...
and so the license to eat meat is restricted by by the
laws of כשרות kashrut and שחיטה. shechita. Right. Right. And and that's
much more about us. Right.
Okay, I see that. I see that. But I again what I
would just say, which I've said before, is that you know, I
don't think that just because a certain value does not apply to
its full extent, doesn't apply outside of the act of שחיטה, shechita,
doesn't apply in let's say some of the technical details, does not
mean that that's not the value that is underlying it. It just
means that it somehow is not being given being given full expression.
And you might even say that the גמרא Gemara doesn't speak with
a single voice.
Well, that's certainly true.
Yes. So I would actually kind of argue the other way. Before
נח, Noach, we could kill animals however we wanted,
we
could do anything we wanted
but eat them. However once we got permission to eat animals we
got אבר מן החי, Ever Min Hachai, which actually puts an in...
so now that we became Jews, we can only שחט shecht animals
we're going to eat. Now as a practical matter today, and I
suspect this was true back in the times of the תלמוד, Talmud,
you never killed an animal for its hide. The only all of
our leather comes from animals that were slaughtered.
Right, it would be terribly wasteful to do that.
It would be way way too expensive. And the processing leather, processing
horns, is just a byproduct. Right. And so in practical matter, we
never kill an animal...
so your basic point is that we're not addressing cases of non-שחיטה
shechita because they are effectively almost non-existent.
For for us, for for Jews, since we
eat stuff through שחיטה, shechita, there's almost no need to address non-שחיטה
shechita cases because they're effectively it's effectively non-existent. Right. That's interesting. Okay.
Okay. So let's now see the
גמרא. Gemara. רבנן מאי שנא רישא דלא פליגי ומאי שנא סיפא דפליגי.
Rabanan mai shena reisha delo paligi u'mai shena seifa depaligi. Why the
rabbis in the beginning did they tell you don't cover the blood
and act as if it's a totally non-good שחיטה shechita and why
in the end do they say don't שחט shecht today, you know,
which might send a signal that it is a good שחיטה? shechita?
Now תוספות Tosafot asks a question which is I said like what
type of question is that? It's one thing to say don't do
a מצוה, mitzvah, it's another thing to give me license to שחט
shecht and maybe do an עבירה. aveira. So even if I am
concerned with the mixed messages people will get, I still can't actively
do an עבירה. aveira. But the גמרא Gemara is somehow bracketing that.
תוספות Tosafot says...
you can look at תוספות. Tosafot. So anyway, the... one of the
first two. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara is bracketing that and the
גמרא Gemara still says, so why are they concerned about impression impressions
in the beginning and not at the end? So the גמרא Gemara
says, ומאי שנא סיפא דפליגי רישא, umai shena seifa depaligi reisha, no,
the beginning, אי אמרינן חייבין לכסות ei amritan chayavin lechasot if we
tell you cover the blood, אמרי שחיטה מעליא היא amrei shechita ma'alya
hee you'll send the message that it was a good שחיטה. shechita.
ואתו למיכל משחיטתם ve-asu l'meichal mishechitatam people will eat from that meat.
סיפא, Seifa, so that's why they say in the beginning cover the
blood. So the גמרא Gemara says, so what? סיפא נמי? seifa nami?
כיון דקאמרי רבנן אסור לשחוט keivan dekameri rabanan assur lishchot even in
the end case why not say the same thing? If they are
saying I can't שחט, shecht, so that's sending a message that it
was a good שחיטה. shechita. אחריהם, achareihem, then after them, then after
them don't שחט shecht after them, אמרי שחיטה מעליא היא amrei shechita
ma'alya hee why aren't we concerned also that'll send a message that
it was a good שחיטה. shechita. ואתו למיכל משחיטתם ve-asu l'meichal mishechitatam
and you'll eat from their שחיטה. shechita. גמרא Gemara says no, like
Michael said, סיפא, seifa, if in the case by not שוחט-ing, shecht
that's not sending a message. You're not doing anything, you're passive. אמרי
בישרא דלא קא מיבעיא ליה, amrei bisra dlo ka mibaya lei,
he's not hungry, he doesn't want meat today. You're not sending a
big message by not שוחט-ing shecht an animal. Okay, but when you
cover the blood... You are sending a message that it was a
good שחיטה. shechita. So the גמרא Gemara says, רישא נמי, Reisha nami,
even the beginning, why are you sending a message? So I mean
maybe you're just covering the blood, why? In order not to לנקות
חצר דצריך lenakot chatzer d'tzarich because you don't like a blood puddle
in your backyard. Okay, maybe you're not doing it because it's good,
maybe you're not sending a message. The גמרא Gemara says no, no,
no, one minute. So שחט באשפה, shachat b'ashpah, מאי איכא למימר? mai
ika l'meimar? Let's say you שחט shacht in your dump heap. You
know, there are places where you would clearly be doing it only
for the מצוה, mitzvah, not because you're trying to keep your yard
clean. Okay, so
בא לימלך, ba l'imlach, מאי איכא למימר? mai ika l'meimar? Let's say
the guy came and said, oh rabbi, do I have to cover
my blood? So if I the blood here, so if I said
yes, I'm he's getting a clear message that this was a good
שחיטה. shechita. So there we have to tell you don't cover it
because there you'd clearly be sending a message that it was a
good שחיטה. shechita. So the גמרא Gemara says לטעמיך, l'teimecha, so the
גמרא Gemara says so what? How about the שחיטה shechting of the
calf after the mother? סיפא נמי, sefa nami, in that case, בא
לימלך, ba l'imlach, מאי איכא למימר? mai ika l'meimar? If the guy
comes and says to me rabbi, what can I שחט shecht this
calf today? According to the end of the משנה, mishnah, I would
have to tell him no. So since I told him no, I'm
I'm sending him the message that it was a good שחיטה. shechita.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying is the concern should exist in
the סיפא sefa as well that if you tell me don't שחט,
shecht, you are sending a message it was a good שחיטה. shechita.
Now again, it's hard to understand what is bothering the גמרא Gemara
so much. Number one, even if there's a little bit of that
concern, it's a much bigger deal when you do a action, both
the message you sent to yourself and the message you send to
other people, then when you just are passively not שחט shechting it.
Even if you got a פסק psak and the rabbi said don't
do it, I'm not telling you the שחיטה shechita is good, but
play it safe or whatever, it's a lot different in that case
than acting on something and covering the blood in terms of the
message I'm sending myself, message I'm sending others. And number two, even
if I was concerned about the message, the rabbis are not going
to give me license to possibly violate a prohibition and to שחט
shecht the calf today. So it's hard to understand what is bothering
the גמרא Gemara so much, but the גמרא Gemara thinks that the
that the רישא reisha and the סיפא sefa should have been consistent.
So let's see what the answer is.
In
the משנה, mishnah, they only argue on the סיפא. sefa.
But it also says פטור patur in the first case.
Oh it doesn't say אסור, assur, right. Right. Because one is a
מצוה, mitzvah, so say to the way saying don't do the מצוה
mitzvah is you're פטור patur from the מצוה, mitzvah, whereas in the
other it's a concern of an עבירה aveirah and we're saying don't
transgress. But you are right, if the right if the concern is
the message you're sending, we don't just want to say you don't
have to cover, we actually want to say you're forbidden to cover.
You're correct about that. That is correct. Okay, let's see what the
גמרא Gemara answers. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא רבנן אכולהו פליגי.
ela rabbanan a'kulhu pligi.
The rabbis argue on everything. The rabbis actually say we don't have
to we're not going to worry about sending messages at all in
general. Good point. So the so the same way we're not going
to worry that when you don't שחט shecht the calf that you're
sending a message that it's a good שחיטה, shechita, we're not going
to worry about the blood also about the message you might send.
And therefore really the rabbis would say cover the blood. Since it
might be good, cover the blood. We're not going to concern ourselves
with the with a possible wrong message. And the same way they
say in the end don't שחט shecht because it might be a
good the first might have been a good
שחיטה. shechita. דשבקוהו לרבי מאיר עד דmסיק ליה למילתיה. d'shavku'hu l'Rabbi Meir
ad d'masik lei l'miltei. They waited until רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir finished
his whole presentation where רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said I treat it
as a definite not good שחיטה shechita and therefore I say don't
cover the blood and therefore I say you can שחט shecht after
them. והדר פליגי עליה, v'hadar pligi alei, and then they argued and
they said we actually treat it as a possible good שחיטה, shechita,
not definitely not good. And since it's possibly good, go ahead and
cover the blood even though it's not in the משנה, mishnah, and
but don't שחט shecht afterwards. So according to this you actually have
no position that says what we thought the משנה mishnah was saying.
We thought the משנה mishnah was saying you know you might be
obligated but you have to be concerned about the messages you're sending.
Now we're saying not that way. We're saying the rabbis basically say
forget about messages, do it you know treat it as a normal
ספק. safek. So if it's a ספק, safek, cover the blood. Don't
make a ברכה. bracha. If it's a ספק, safek, don't שחט shecht
afterwards. Don't worry about any messages you're sending. And רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says I consider it to be definitely not good. Since it's
definitely not good don't cover the blood and not only don't cover
the blood you can even שחט shecht on the same day. Okay
so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's definitely not good, the rabbis
say it's it's a doubt and play it safe and nobody says
like be concerned about what message you might be sending. So now
let's see how the גמרא Gemara deals with it. בשלמא רבנן לחומרא.
bishlama rabbanan l'chumra.
So the rabbis are being strict. Maybe it's good maybe it's not
good play it safe. Cover the blood don't שחט shecht on the
same day. אלא רבי מאיר מאי טעמא? ela Rabbi Meir mai ta'ama?
Why is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir saying it's definitely not good and
he lets you שחט shecht even on the same day? So אמר
רבי יעקב אמר רבי יוחנן מחייב היה רבי מאיר על שחיטתן משום
נבלה amar Rabbi Yaakov amar Rabbi Yochanan mechayiv haya Rabbi Meir al
shechitatan mishum neveilah because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir yeah said the שחיטה
shechita of a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan if you're not
observing it is definitely not good and if you eat from the
meat it's like you ate from נבלה, neveilah, he'd even give you
lashes. Okay. because the vast, I'm saying vast, he doesn't say vast,
but the majority of cases, most times a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shotte v'katan שחט, shecht, they ruin it. And we know there's a
principle, you go by רוב. rov. So it's not just a ספק.
safek. You actually go by רוב rov and you make an assumption
based on that majority that it was a not good שחיטה. shchita.
So based on that assumption, we'll give you lashes if you eat
it for נבלה. neveila. Based on that assumption, we'll say you can
cover the... don't cover the blood and you can שחט shacht the
calf on the same day. We make, you know, we start with
saying what was the story with this שחיטה? shchita? So rather than
saying, 'oh, I don't know, play it safe, whatever,' make a decision.
So the decision is, go by the majority, we're going to assume
it was not good.
Wait one second. But so, yeah. Eventually we're going to get to
this, so isn't... isn't רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir the one who's חושש
למיעוטא? choshesh l'miyuta?
We're getting there, next line, yeah.
All right. He said do a second שחיטה? shchita?
No, not on the same animal. You can שחט shacht the calf
of the same day. If you שחט shacht the mother, if the
חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shotte v'katan שחט shacht the mother, you can
assume it was a not valid שחיטה shchita and therefore you're allowed
to שחט shacht the calf on the same day.
Wait, did you say something somebody said about the second שחיטה? shchita?
No.
I might have said it, but I meant שחט shacht the calf.
Okay. So that's what רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says. Now, he's not
saying that they're categorically excluded. If they were observed and observed to
have done it correctly, it would be good. But if they were
not observed, we can just assume it was not good. So now
we have the rabbis deal with it as a ספק safek and
they say, 'play it safe, don't concern yourself about sending messages.' And
רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says, 'it's definitely not good and you work
from there.' So אמר ליה רב פפא לרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע,
Amar lei Rav Pappa l'Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua, so רב פפא
Rav Pappa said to רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Rav Huna brei
d'Rav Yehoshua, ואמרי לה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרב פפא, v'amri
la Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua l'Rav Pappa, or some say it
went the reverse way. מאי איריא רוב? mai irya rov? Like Michael
said, why, if you want to defend רבי מאיר's Rebbe Meir position,
you have to say the majority is not good? אפילו מיעוטא נמי,
afillu miyuta nami, even a minority. Now, why should it go the
other way? דהא, d'ha, let's see, רבי מאיר חייש למיעוטא. Rebbe Meir
chayish l'miyuta. רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir normally is concerned for a minority.
Now, the concern for a minority means be strict. If a certain
minority of cases are problem, רבי מאיר's Rebbe Meir general position is
that we have to attend to those minority of cases. Here, what's
the logic? So if a minority of חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shotte
v'katan do it bad, how should that lead us to saying that
it's definitely bad? Right? If anything, Michael was saying the opposite question.
Even if the majority, even if the majority do it bad, how
can we ignore the minority that do it good and that leads
to possible restrictions? So let's see, you're right, great question. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says with this. So דהא רבי מאיר
חייש למיעוטא, d'ha Rebbe Meir chayish l'miyuta, סמוך מיעוטא לחזקה ואיתרע ליה
רובא. smoch miyuta l'chazaka v'itrei lei rova.
So here's an interesting irony that comes from רבי מאיר. Rebbe Meir.
Once רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir gives weight to the minority, we also
know that when that minority joins up with the חזקה, chazaka, we
assume that we follow the חזקה chazaka and we ignore the majority.
What's the case? So let me tell you sort of how we're
going to apply it here and then we'll see the other case
the גמרא Gemara brings in. The animal starts with the חזקה chazaka
of not being שחט-ed, shacht right? It's alive, it's mooing. So it's
not שחט-ed, shacht it's a חזקה chazaka of not being שחט-ed. shacht
Now, you need an act to change that status quo. So, even
if, says the גמרא, Gemara, a majority of חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shotte v'katan would do it correctly, that's not enough to change the
status quo. Since רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir gives weight to the minority
possibility, even if it was just a minority that did it bad,
so if you have the significant, you have a minority possibility that
you can't ignore that it might not have been done correctly and
the status quo was that it was not good, then you can't
change the status quo and you have to assume that it remains
not good. So the irony that comes from רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir
is, although רבי מאיר's Rebbe Meir normally strict and he says you
can't ignore the minority possibility, you have to attend to it, you
have to be strict, but the logical consequence of that is also
that he gives weight to the minority possibility in general. So not
just to be strict. So therefore here, even if the majority of
חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shotte v'katan did a bad... did a good
job, once there's a minority that does a bad job, you cannot
change the status quo of the animal of being not kosher, of
being not
שחט-ed.
shacht But why don't you cover the blood then? Because right, since
it started out...
we can just assume it's definitely not good, correct. So the גמרא
Gemara says, why do you have to say for רבי מאיר Rebbe
Meir the majority did it bad? Even if the minority did it
bad, since he gives weight to the minority, that should be enough
to keep the animal in its status of not being kosher. Okay,
now where do you see רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says
this? ואיתרע ליה רובא, v'itrei lei rova, and that weighs more or
undermines the רוב. rov. דתנן, d'tnan, we taught in the משנה. Mishna.
תינוק שנמצא בצד העיסה, tinok shenimtza b'tzad ha-issa, you have an infant
that's found next to some dough. ובצק בידו, u-vatzek b'yado, and he
has a little piece of the dough in his hand. So רבי
מאיר מטהר, Rebbe Meir metaher, רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says the dough
is still טהור. tahor. וחכמים מטמאין, vachachamim m'tam'in, they say it's טמא.
tamei. Why? מפני שדרכו של תינוק לטפח, mipnei she-darko shel tinok l'tapeach,
because kids usually sort of, you know, get their hands in everything.
Now what did they get their hands in? So רש"י Rashi says
it means they probably touched some type of a bug and therefore
then they... and now they're holding the dough, so we have to
assume that they touched a bug and then they made the dough
טמא. tamei. תוספות Tosafot says no, no, no, actually we assume that
a תינוק tinok is טמא. tamei. Why? Because... Who's normally handling a
תינוק? tinok? His mother or women, and they're a most of the
good part of the time they're נדות. niddas. So therefore we actually
assume that the תינוק tinok is טמא. tamei. The question is did
the תינוק tinok touch the dough? Now he's holding the dough. Ah,
so know the dough that he's holding he touched. Did he touch
the rest of the dough? Well, of course. How else did he
get the
dough? No, maybe somebody came, "Oh, you cute little kid here let
me give you a piece of dough," and somebody else gave it
to him. So the question is did the תינוק tinok himself touch
the rest of the dough or did somebody give it to him?
So the rabbis say look normally kids get their hands in everything
we have to assume that the kid touched the dough. But רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says no, it's טהור. tahor. Why? ואמרינן, ve'amrinan, and
we say, מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר, mai ta'ama deRabbi Meir, what's the
reasoning of רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? קסבר kasavar רוב תינוקות מטפחין, rov
tinokot metapchin, it's true majority of kids are tap, sort of patting
all over, getting their hands on everything. ומיעוט אין מטפחין, umiut ein
metapchin, but there is a minority that aren't. ועיסה זו בחזקת טהרה
עומדת, ve'isa zo bechezkat taharah omedet, and this dough started off being
טהור. tahor. It had a status quo of being טהור. tahor. סמוך
מיעוטא לחזקה, semoch miuta lechazakah, so you take the minority possibility, which
is significant, which we don't ignore, we pay attention to minority, you
add it to the status quo. You have a status quo which
was טהור. tahor. You have the possibility that it remained that, although
it's only a
minority. ואיתרע ליה רובא, ve'itra lei ruba, the majority possibility that the
תינוק tinok touched it and changed the status does not, is not
strong enough to change its status quo. So here you see that
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says basically, simply, a רוב rov doesn't change
a status quo. Since he gives weight, a רוב rov is not
the end of the final say, there is also the minority, that
has weight. Therefore a רוב rov is not enough to change it.
So if that's true, even if a majority of חרש שוטה וקטן
cheresh shoteh vekatan did a bad job, right, it should not change
the status quo of the cow of being not שחטed shecht and
being not kosher. So why did you have to say for רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir that he assumes a majority do it incorrectly? So
let's see the answer. So the גמרא Gemara says, אם אמרו ספק
טומאה לטהר יאמרו ספק איסור להתיר? im amru safek tumah letaher yomeru
safek issur lehatir? Just because he says that something, it's enough for
something to remain טהור, tahor, doesn't mean he would say it's enough
to allow you to possibly do a prohibition and to שחט shecht
the calf on the same day. Now what is the difference? Okay,
I mean, if you say
the dough is
טהור, tahor, maybe it's תרומה terumah and maybe you'll do a prohibition
by assuming it's
טהור. tahor. So why should there be a difference? The גמרא Gemara
doesn't spell it out. One way could be that the difference is
the following. By the
dough, we're saying it keeps its status, it remains טהור. tahor. That's
what we're saying. Fine, it remains טהור. tahor. We're just going to
assume no change of status. By the case by, let's say the
חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan that שחטed shecht the cow, we're
not just saying the meat retains its status and it's not kosher.
We're going to actually allow you to do something new. We're going
to allow you now to go ahead and שחט shecht the calf.
So to allow you to do something new is like moving away
from just saying this meat retains its status to drawing other inferences
from it and licensing some other behavior. Okay, so that may be
seen as something that's categorically different, we're not willing to make the
jump. That's one way of reading it. תוספות Tosafot says another point.
תוספות Tosafot says that laws of טומאה וטהרה, tumah vetaharah, as you
might know, follow their own sort of logic. And one of the
logics is, is that if you have a ספק safek by טומאה
וטהרה, tumah vetaharah, you can often go lenient, especially if it's in
רשות הרבים reshut harabbim and other types of criteria. So תוספות Tosafot
says that maybe this issue for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is enough
to make it like a 50/50. And a 50/50 for טומאה וטהרה
tumah vetaharah you can be lenient, because that has certain rules that
allow you to be lenient, but for other things it does not.
So the גמרא Gemara makes a distinction, but it doesn't really spell
out the logic of the distinction. But the upshot is maybe for
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir it would have been enough to say a
minority do a bad job, but certainly if he says that a
majority do a bad job, he's able to say that it is
definitely not good and therefore we can draw all the consequences. You'll
get lashes for an עבירה, aveirah, you don't cover the blood, you're
allowed to שחט shecht the calf on the same day. You had
a question?
Yeah, sometimes you might do something with the dough that would be
another thing, that would be another מצוה. mitzvah.
That's true too. But again, the way I sort of see the
simplest distinction of the גמרא Gemara is there you're just making a
ruling about the dough, and everything afterwards is going to be continuing
the status of the dough. Whereas here, you're giving license to another
activity that doesn't even relate to this cow. You're saying go שחט
shecht the calf, right? So that may be the bigger jump. Let's
finish up this point. Okay, הורה רבי כרבי מאיר, horah Rabbi keRabbi
Meir, רבי Rabbi ruled like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that actually said
it was definitely not good and you can draw all the consequences.
והורה רבי כחכמים, vehorah Rabbi keChachamim, but then he gave another ruling,
it's like Rav Soloveitchik, some people say he said this, some people
say he said that, but to this person he said this, to
that person he said that. So anyway, so רבי Rabbi for one
place ruled like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and in another place he
ruled like the חכמים Chachamim that says it was doubtful and you
have to do sort of play safe both ways. הי מנייהו דבתרייתא,
hei mineihu debatrayta, which one was his last ruling, which would be
the authoritative one? So תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, דאמר
רב אבא בריה דרב חייא בר אבא ורבי זירא הוו קיימי בשוקא
דקיסרי, de'amar Rav Abba bereih deRav Chiya bar Abba veRabbi Zeira havu
kaimei beshuka deKeisari,
they were there in the marketplace of Caesarea. Caesarea. אפתחא דבי
מדרשא. apitcha devei midrasha. And they were in the marketplace, they had
some shopping to do, and they were standing outside of the opening
of the בית המדרש, Beis HaMedrash, which was near the marketplace, but
they weren't going into the בית המדרש, Beis HaMedrash, they had some
shopping to do. Okay, so נפיק רבי אמי, nafik Rabbi Ami, so
Rabbi Ami came out, אשכחינהו, ashkachinhu, he saw them there in the
market. אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to them, לאו אמינא לכו,
lav amina lechu, haven't I told you, בעידן בית מדרשא, be'idan beis
midrasha, at the time of the בית המדרש, Beis HaMedrash, לא תקימו
אבראי, lo tekimu avrai, don't stay outside. Now they apparently were not
students, and he wasn't a truant officer, they were actually people that
he needed in the בית המדרש Beis HaMedrash to help out with
the teaching. So he says, I know you're
רבנים rebbeiyim and you had some shopping to do, but you guys
have to be in the בית המדרש Beis HaMedrash when the בית
המדרש Beis HaMedrash is going. Okay, דילמא איכא איניש dilma ika inish
דמצטרכא ליה שמעתא, demitztracha leh shmayta, maybe somebody is
learning some topic that they have a difficulty with and they need
your help, ואתי למיטרד ve'asi lemitrad and they're going to get confused
because you're not there to help them. So guys, you gotta be
in the בית המדרש Beis HaMedrash to answer questions during בית המדרש
Beis HaMedrash hours. So רבי זירא על, Rabbi Zeira al, Rabbi Zeira
listened, he went into the בית המדרש. Beis HaMedrash. רבי אבא לא
על, Rabbi Abba lo al, Rabbi Abba said, I'm sorry, I got
my shopping to do. Okay, so now יתבי וקמיבעיא להו, yasvi vekamibaya
lehu, so they were in the בית המדרש Beis HaMedrash and they
were asking the question, הי מינייהו אחריתא, hai minaihu achreita, which ruling
of רבי Rebbi was the last one? Did he rule like the
חכמים Chakhamim or did he rule like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir about
the שחיטה shechita of a חרש שוטה וקטן? cheresh shoteh vekatan? Is
it doubtful or is it definitely not good? So אמר ליה רבי
זירא, amar leh Rabbi Zeira, so Rabbi Zeira said, לא שבקיתון לי
דאישאיל לסבא, lo shvakitun li de'isha'il lesaba,
you didn't give me the opportunity or I didn't sort of know
that this was the question, because then I would have asked
the elder. Who's the elder? רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba, who was the
one who stayed out in the marketplace. So you see, he really
should have gone in, because רבי אבא Rabbi Abba had the goods,
רבי אבא Rabbi Abba had the answer. And he said, och, you
didn't give me the opportunity or I didn't realize that this question,
because then I could have asked רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba. דילמא שמיע
ליה, dilma shmia leh, now why does רבי אבא Rabbi Abba have
the answer? Because maybe he heard מאבוה, me'avuha, from his
father. Okay, this was רבי אבא Rabbi Abba the son of רבי
חייא בר אבא. Rabbi Chiya bar Abba. So he was the son
of רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. So he maybe heard from his father
רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, ואבוה, ve'avuha, his father, מרבי יוחנן, meRabbi Yochanan,
because his father רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya was a student of
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. And רבי חייא בר אבא, Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba, and how do we know that רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba was a student and got the goods from רבי
יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? כל תלתין יומין קמהדר תלמודיה קמי דרבי יוחנן, kol
taltin yomin kamahader talmudei kamei deRabbi Yochanan, every thirty days he would
review all of his learning in front of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
to erase any questions he might have had. So maybe it means
every thirty days he would visit and ask any questions, it's hard
to know exactly fully what that means. But anyway, so his father
was in constant conversation with רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, so his father
might have asked this from רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. How would we
assume רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan knew? Not exactly clear, but somehow there
was an assumption that maybe רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan knew what רבי's
Rebbi's ruling was. So anyway, they didn't have the answer and unfortunately
רבי אבא Rabbi Abba didn't come into the בית המדרש Beis HaMedrash
so we couldn't ask him.
So then the next day,
I don't know, מאי הוה עלה, mai hava alah, what was the
upshot? תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, דשלח רבי אלעזר לגולה,
deshalach Rabbi Elazar lagolah, Rabbi Elazar sent to the exile: הורה רבי
כרבי מאיר, hora Rebbi keRabbi Meir, רבי Rebbi ruled like רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. Which so, so the גמרא Gemara says, והא רבנן אמרי,
veha rabanan amri, what do you mean he ruled like רבי מאיר?
Rabbi Meir? We also have a tradition that he ruled like the
rabbis. אלא לאו, ela lav, since that was the only message he
sent, שמע מינה הדא אחריתא, shma mina hada achreita, this was the
definitive one and this was the last ruling of רבי. Rebbi. שמע
מינה, shma mina, that is a good proof. So therefore we say
that actually, surprisingly, although we started with saying if a חרש שוטה
וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan שחט shachat you can't eat from it, we
actually probably assumed until now that it was doubtful, but now we're
actually saying that רבי Rebbi ruled like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
that it is definitely not good and therefore you can even be
lenient in a way and שחט לכתחילה shachat lechatchila afterwards on the
same day. Okay, we have a few more minutes. Let's start the
next גמרא. Gemara. It's very quick, so let's see where we can
get in the next four minutes. Okay. שחט מאה חיות במקום אחד,
shachat mea chayos bemakom echad, let's say you שחט shachat a hundred
חיות chayos all in the same place. כיסוי אחד לכולן, kisuy echad
lekulan, you don't have to do a separate covering of every שחיטה.
shechita. You wait till you finish all your שחיטות shechitos and do
one covering of all the blood. Yeah, all the bloods are collected.
מאה עופות במקום אחד, mea ofos bemakom echad, or a hundred birds,
כיסוי אחד לכולן, kisuy echad lekulan, certainly makes it easier, probably pay
more per bird for our Empire chickens if they had to stop
every minute and cover the blood. Okay.
Now, חיה ועוף במקום אחד, chaya va'of bemakom echad,
let's say you שחט shachat a deer and a bird and a
chicken in the same place. Also כיסוי אחד לכולן, kisuy echad lekulan,
cover them together. And here רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda takes issue. רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, Rabbi Yehuda says, שחט חיה יכסנה ואחר
כך ישחוט את העוף. shachat chaya yachasena ve'achar kach yishchot es ha'of.
No, since the תורה Torah says שחט חיה או עוף, shachat chaya
o of, it distinguishes them, so therefore your covering should be a
different covering for a חיה chaya and a different covering for a
bird. Today is Tuesday, oh my god, I forgot, okay, we're ending
now.